[Music]
testosterone is linked with sexual
desire in both men and women women
normally produce testosterone throughout
the life cycle although postmenopausal
ovaries continue to produce testosterone
levels naturally decline with age
testosterone blood levels decrease
approximately 50% by age 50 which may
play a role in the decline in libido
using masturbation frequency as a
partner independent proxy A syndrome of
female Androgen deficiency symptoms has
been popularized but there's no evidence
testosterone replacement helps with mood
or well-being hot flashes or bone
cardiovascular or metabolic Health the
only evidence-based reason to try
testosterone in post-menopausal women is
for the treatment of low sexual desire
that causes distress a systematic review
and meta analysis of three dozen
randomized control trials involv Ving
more than 8,000 women found that
testosterone treatment significantly
increased postmenopausal sexual desire
the increase in frequency of
satisfactory sexual events was
statistically significant but not
clinically significant enough to Warrant
FDA approval especially given the
uncertainty about long-term side effects
the women on testosterone only logged a
little under one additional satisfactory
sexual event a month compared to placebo
currently there are more than 30 FDA
prooved testosterone products for men
but none for women clinicians can trial
a few months of a male transdermal
testosterone preparation at one/ Tenth
the dose or less making sure to check
levels to prevent overdosing which can
have virilizing side effects such as
clitoral enlargement and voice changes
even at premenopausal physiological
doses testosterone can cause acne and
excessive hair growth on the chin cheeks
and upper lip unlike oral testosterone
formulations administered through the
skin don't appear to have the same
negative effects on cholesterol levels
but long-term safety data for women
regarding cardiovascular cancer and
cognitive outcomes are lacking it has
been estimated more than a fifth of
prescriptions for male testosterone
products are actually written for women
and this is not including custom
compounded testosterone a consensus
position statement of International
Medical Society specializing in hormone
issues recommends against compounded
bioidentical testosterone due to a lack
of evidence for efficacy and safety
similarly the dietary supplement DHEA
which can convert into testosterone
within the body cannot be recommended
for low libido and women since a
metaanalysis of more than 20 randomized
control trials found no significant
effect on improving desire and sexual
function are there any natural ways for
women to raise their testosterone levels
listening to music for just 30 minutes
can increase testosterone levels in
young women by about
20% interestingly the opposite effect
was found in men for more on the effects
of Music check out my video music as
medicine heavy mint consumption can
lower testosterone levels in both men
and women there are case reports of men
drinking four cups a day of spearmint or
peppermint tea losing their sex drive
given the apparent anti-androgenic
effects researchers decided to try it
out on women concerned about excessive
hairiness and in a matter of just 5 days
were able to drop their free
testosterone levels by about 30% with
two cups of minty a day there's a
syndrome called Pea or polycystic
ovarian syndrome which can result in
abnormally high testosterone levels in
women which can be successfully brought
down with mint tea but for women
struggling with low libido it might not
be a good
[Music]
choice